<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the assizes in Leicester, July 31, 1679 by John Cave.</title>
            <author>Cave, John, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31406</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">7922233</idno>
  <idno type="VID">40471</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248543177</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23914</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">07922233</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1201:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the assizes in Leicester, July 31, 1679 by John Cave.</title>
                  <author>Cave, John, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Clark for Richard Chiswel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Micah IV, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40471:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40471:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES IN <hi>LEICESTER. July</hi> 31. 1679.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>JOHN CAVE,</hi> Rector of <hi>Cold-Overton</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire,</hi> and Chaplain to my Lord Bishop of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Our help is in the Name of the Lord who made heaven and earth.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. cxxiv. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Clark,</hi> for <hi>Richard Chiswel</hi> at the Rose and Crown in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40471:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40471:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worshipful <hi>ROWLAND BROWN</hi> Esq; High Sheriff of the County of <hi>LEICESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THIS Sermon which was Preached at your request, is by the kind acceptance of my <hi>Lords</hi> the <hi>Judges,</hi> and of <hi>your self</hi> encouraged to become more publick. God knows my chief end both in Preaching and Printing it, is to engage all men, but more especially men of <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> not only in a diligent and <hi>exemplary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> but also in a <hi>zealous</hi> and <hi>resolute defence</hi> of Religion, of <hi>the Establisht Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> a <hi>Religion</hi> which above all other teacheth us not only to be <hi>Godly,</hi> but to be <hi>Honest;</hi> a <hi>Religion</hi> not only <hi>pure</hi> but <hi>peaceable,</hi> full of the good fruits of Loyalty, Justice, Charity, <hi>without Partiality</hi> and <hi>without Hypocrisie:</hi> And sure all sober and good men cannot but look upon it as their greatest
<pb facs="tcp:40471:3"/>interest, as well in respect of <hi>this life,</hi> as of <hi>that which is to come,</hi> to uphold the power and honor of this <hi>Religion,</hi> which is so true a friend of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> so sure a defence of our Civil Rights, and which, if we submit to its Laws, and cherish its Influences, will make us truly happy, both <hi>here</hi> and <hi>hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, if you had not been otherwise entitled to this <hi>Sermon,</hi> your <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Patronage</hi> of its Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine would have made it <hi>yours,</hi> for indeed your affection to so good a Cause, in very difficult and discouraging Circumstances hath been generally taken notice of, for your <hi>Honour;</hi> and your <hi>Zeal</hi> hath been so well tempered and governed by your <hi>prudence,</hi> that our most notorious defamers have not yet had the confidence to touch your reputation.</p>
            <p>That you may continue to <hi>walk</hi> in that <hi>name</hi> which will advance and secure <hi>yours,</hi> and give you a <hi>Renown</hi> more solid and durable than any convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from <hi>Ancestors,</hi> or any dignity which is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from an <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Trust</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>Your most faithful<lb/> and obliged friend and servant<lb/>
                  <hi>JOHN CAVE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40471:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES IN <hi>LEICESTER, July</hi> 31. 1679.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MICAH iv. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For all people will walk every one in the name of his God, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God, for ever and ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>GOD having in the foregoing Chapter by his Prophet denounced severe threatnings against his people, and even an utter deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his <hi>own mountain, that place of his habitation which he had chosen for himself,</hi> which he had furnished and beautified with so many signs of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40471:4"/>Majesty and his Gracious presence (to shew how much he <hi>delights to remember mercy even in the midst of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>) In the beginning of this Chapter he relieves their despair by discovering to them a Sun behind their Cloud, and giving them a comfortable prospect into better times: <hi>In the last days it shall come to pass that the mountain of the house of the Lord shall be established in the top of the mountains,</hi> &amp;c. Which Prophesie though it chiefly respects the coming of the <hi>Messiah,</hi> and the exalted state of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> made illustrious not by outward pomps but by spiritual priviledges, yet it seems to have regard also to a time not so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, <hi>viz.</hi> the time of their return from the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Captivity,</hi> that then together with their Liberty they should have their <hi>Religion</hi> restored, and <hi>reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> they should <hi>worship the Lord in the beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness;</hi> and the <hi>house</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> should overtop all the <hi>high places</hi> of the false Gods. None of the Hills wherein the <hi>Pagans</hi> worship their <hi>Idols</hi> shall be any way compared with the transcendent glory of <hi>Mount Moriah,</hi> or honoured with so general a Devotion: For hither shall flock the true worshippers from sever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al parts of the world, and <hi>many Nations shall come and say; Come let us go up to the mountain of the Lord and to the house of the God of</hi> Jacob, (which was a Type of the Church or Kingdom of Christ) and <hi>he will teach us</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by his Priests and Prophets what is fittest for us to learn) <hi>out of his ways, that we may walk in them:</hi> For from thence only must we look for the knowledg of the true God, <hi>whose Law</hi> (especially in the days of the Messiah) shall go forth of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the word of the Lord from <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> from whence it shall be derived and promulged to the rest of the world: To make their condition still more happy and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40471:4"/>to endear their Religion to them by a concomitance of earthly blessings, such as Liberty and Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their great and good <hi>God</hi> will for their sakes <hi>judg</hi> among <hi>many People,</hi> and <hi>rebuke strong Nations after of such</hi> as <hi>were</hi> too <hi>mighty</hi> and <hi>puissant</hi> for <hi>them</hi> to graple withal: by the sweet yet most prevalent force of his word and spirit he will quiet the most turbulent and quarrelsom tempers, persuade them out of all their animosities, and so throughly pacifie them that they shall turn their weapons of war into the Utensils of peaceful times: <hi>Their swords into plough-shares, and their spears into pruning books, Then shall every man sit quietly under his own vine and under his own fig-tree, and none shall make them afraid:</hi> These were the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings promised more immediately in some kind to the <hi>Jews</hi> upon their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> but more amply and in the best sense injoyed by us under the <hi>Gospel,</hi> who have the <hi>substance</hi> of their <hi>Type.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words of my Text give us an account of the motive of this great mercy of God, namely his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples sidelity and constancy in his service, for upon this they seem to ground their confidence and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance of the Divine Blessing: <hi>viz.</hi> the sincerity and stedfastness of their resolution to adhere to his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and keep his Commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We will walk in the name of the Lord our God:</hi> and because we are resolved to serve him and to trust in him, we doubt not of his Favour and Patronage, we doubt not of the fulfilling of all his gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and that he <hi>will be with us while we are with him, and will never forsaks us unless we depart from him;</hi> which we are resolved now to do no more, our Heads or Magistrates shall no more judg for reward, nor our Priests teach for hire, nor our People fight
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40471:5"/>for Religion, <hi>build</hi> up <hi>Sion</hi> with <hi>blood,</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem</hi> with <hi>iniquity;</hi> we are resolved no more to follow vain Idols, but to be as diligent and zealous in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the true God, as the most Superstitious Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens are in the worship of their false Deities, and in so doing we promise our selves the benefits of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Protection. And indeed what need we fear who adhere to the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> against whom neither the subtlety, malice, power of our Enemies, nor any other Gods can prevail?</p>
            <p>This seems to be the ground of the inference whereby these words are connected with the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verses.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For all people will walk every one in the name of his God, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Doctors, as the Learned <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> hath observed, expound the words thus, <hi>Till that time all people shall walk in the name of their Gods, and shall not turn into the right way of Religion, until the</hi> King Messiah <hi>convert them into it; But we of the house of</hi> Israel <hi>will walk in the name of our God for ever, though the Temple be destroyed and we led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives out of our Land, yet we will never change our God, but continue faithful in his service.</hi> Another gives us this sence of the words: <hi>All people which now walk every one in the name of his God, and we also the sons of</hi> Israel, <hi>all of us, both we and they, in the Gospel days, will walk in the name of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed I think we shall not much mistake our selves if we understand the words to signifie the reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Gospel Converts, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to renounce all irregular Worship, all Heresie and Schism, and to be constantly and zealously devoted to the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40471:5"/>of God, to the profession and practice of the Christian Religion, exciting themselves hereunto by the example of Idolaters who were so pertinacious and obstinate in a false way of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For all men will walk every one in the name of his God, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my Discourse upon these words I shall endeavour to demonstrate these three things unto you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all people, the most ignorant and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations will have a God and a Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That those who are Educated or ingaged in a Superstitious, Idolatrous, or any other false way of worship, are very hardly convinced of their errors and drawn off from them: <hi>All people will walk every one in the name of his God,</hi> of what he believes, nay of what he fancies to be so.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we Christians who have so clear and full a knowledg of the true God, and such rational induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and encouragements to serve him, are most strictly obliged to <hi>keep his holy will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to walk in the same all the days of our lives, to walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever:</hi> Of these in their order, and first of the first.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All People and Nations even the most ignorant and barbarous will have a Religion, every man will have a God to walk in his name, to advance himself by his Relation to a better being, and to perform such service and homage to him as he imagines will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his interest in his favour.</p>
            <p>Those who cannot attain to the right knowledg of the true God, will yet either receive from others or frame to themselves some Image of him. <hi>Omnibus de Diis opinio insita est,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note>
               <hi>nec ulla Gens adeo est extra leges moresque posita ut non aliquos, Deos credat:</hi> The noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40471:6"/>of a God doth naturally arise out of the being of a man, neither is there any Nation so lawless and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred as to believe there is no God.</p>
            <p>They will have many <hi>Gods</hi> rather than none at all, and worship any thing rather than want a <hi>Deity,</hi> which although it shewed their great stupidity: yet it argues for the being of one true God, because their would be no Counterfeit, but for the sake of som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is real: But seeing we want not their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to serve our cause, but have many better argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to evince the existence of one God: I think we may do them so much right as to acknowledg that they may almost, if not altogether, as fairly acquit themselves of <hi>Polytheism</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> as our <hi>Roman Christians,</hi> and prove that <hi>they</hi> attributed no more <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> to their <hi>Daemons</hi> and <hi>Heroes</hi> than <hi>these</hi> do to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> bowed with no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and no less reason, to any part of the inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate world, than <hi>these</hi> do to an <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Crucifix,</hi> nor in any of their fond Rites and Ceremonies excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the degrees of <hi>these</hi> mens Superstition.</p>
            <p>But without carrying on this Comparison any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, perhaps it might be made appear that not only every man hath owned a God: but that most, if not all men have owned the same God under several Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, with respect to the several benefits they received from him, it was that <hi>one true God</hi> whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> Preached that the <hi>men of</hi> Athens <hi>ignorantly Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts xvii. 23. Lib. 1.8.3.</note>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> tell us <hi>that no wise man ever questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the being of one God who made and governed all things, though they worshipped him under different names.</hi> And <hi>Paulus Orosious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hist. l. 6. c. 1.</note> who lived in St. <hi>Augustines</hi> time, assures us, <hi>that not only the Philosophers found out one God the maker of all things, but that the generality of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40471:6"/>Pagans of their times, when the Christians disputed with them, did confess that there was but one great God who had several Ministers under him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what have we more plain than that of a <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sopher</hi> of their own, Maximus Tyrius,<note place="margin">Dissert. 1.</note>
               <hi>Notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the variety of disputes, difference of Opinions, and modes of worship that are in several parts of the world, there is a Catholick agreement in this:</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that there is one God the King and Father of all, and that the many Gods besides are the sons and substitutes of this one supream.</hi> I cannot stay to produce more Testimonies of this Nature, and I hope enough hath been said to make good the first propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, That all people do unanimously concur in this belief and persuasion, that there is a God. Every man will have a God, a Religion, he that hath not is scarce a man, he hath strangely degraded and debased his nature.</p>
            <p>For this seems to be the great essential difference between men and brutes that these have no knowledg of a God;<note place="margin">Nullum est Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal praeter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem quod ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat aliquam notitiam Dei-Solus enim sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus est, ut reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem solus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligat, &amp; haec est hominis at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que brutorum vel praecipua vel sola distantia. <hi>Cic. lib. 1. de legibus.</hi>
               </note> though they have some resemblance if not some degrees of Reason, yet they have nothing at all like Religion, hence it is that for the most part sensuality is the first step to Atheism, and the more brutish men become in their affections and practices, the less do <hi>they like to retain God in their knowledg.</hi> And therefore not to leave this Head without some practical reflection.</p>
            <p>To what can we impute the spreading of Atheism, and the worst sort of Infidelity among our selves, but to the prevalency of vice, the debauchery of our lives, the general corruption and depravity of mens manners, their habitual intemperance in several kinds? We are naturally born to as good a stock of Reason
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40471:7"/>as our Forefathers were, and we have had as good helps of improvement as any age hath afforded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides a most clear and well-attested Revelation, and therefore it were impossible that we should fall so far short of their knowledg, and reason, at a rate so much below the men of the darkest times, if we had not first besotted our selves by indulging our senses, and wasted the strength and vigour of our minds in the service of some infatuating Lust. For where Nature and Reason, as you have heard, can but hold their own, Religion will keep its footing, and every man will have a God, in whose name to walk. But to proceed; <hi>Ʋt omnes Religione moventur,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> speaks, as all men, all sorts of men, nor only <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> but the most rude and uncultivated people have some sense of Religion: <hi>Ita,</hi> as <hi>he goes</hi> on, <hi>Deos Patrios quos acceperunt à majoribus suis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendos sibique retinendos arbitrantur:</hi> So they think <hi>themselves</hi> not <hi>only</hi> bound to <hi>honour</hi> their <hi>Country Gods,</hi> the Gods of their Fathers, <hi>with some pious rites,</hi> such as Sacrifice, Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but also to be constant in their superstition: and not to change their Gods, or to vary in their worship, upon any consideration which is in effect my second</p>
            <p n="2">2. Proposition, <hi>viz.</hi> That those who are educated or ingaged in a Superstitious Idolatrous or any false or factious way of worship, are hardly convinced of their errors and drawn off from them, <hi>All men will walk every man in the name of his God,</hi> of what he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to be so. This is strongly affirmed in that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of the <hi>Prophet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. ii. 11.</note>
               <hi>Hath a Nation changed their Gods, which yet are no Gods? Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> observes that this was the great hinderance of the Heathens Conversion to Christianity <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40471:7"/>&amp;c. They thought it a very unseemly and unreasonable thing to recede from the Traditions of their Fathers, and the Religious Ceremonies and observances they had been accustomed to from their youth. And he goeth on to shew that nothing else could so much obstruct the entertainment and esteem of Christian Religion as this pestilent and stubborn humour of retaining old Laws and Customs, though never so absurd and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous.</p>
            <p>From this dotage, and most wretched influence of Custom, ariseth a hatred of the best Religion: It could not be that they should distast, and refuse the greatest blessing which God ever offered them, if their Palates were not habituated to worse fare, and their affections taken up for some Old Guests.</p>
            <p>Unpon which account <hi>Athenagoras</hi> might well won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that among all the Laws which were yearly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted at <hi>Rome,</hi> there was never a one made, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to abate the force of Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to Establish a liberty of distinguishing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Old and Good, and to renew that great and universal Charter which allows us to judg and chuse for our selves. For he makes it evidently appear, that if the prevalency of ridiculous Customs were once disanulled, their Idol Temples would be no more througed with Votaries: Reason would bear sway, and Christianity triumph over all its superstitious op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers.</p>
            <p>Yea, It is plain that this was the great and unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able prejudice against St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine,<note place="margin">Acts xvii. 18. Acts xvi. 21.</note> when he Preached <hi>Jesus</hi> and the <hi>Resurrection,</hi> that it was <hi>new</hi> and <hi>strange,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were before accused for <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing customs which were not lawful for them to receive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40471:8"/>Romans:</hi> For the <hi>Romans then</hi> pleaded as much for Antiquity as they do <hi>now:</hi> they were impatient of any <hi>Reformation in Religion,</hi> however reasonable and necessary, because as <hi>Dio Chrysostom</hi> observes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>they knew this would alter their Laws too,</hi> which <hi>Rome Imperial</hi> could not brook, she must and will be <hi>infallible</hi> and <hi>supream,</hi> merely because she hath been long reputed so.</p>
            <p>This was it which confirmed the <hi>Samaritans</hi> in their <hi>Superstition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John iv. 20.</note>
               <hi>Our Fathers worshipped in this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi> The <hi>vain Conversation</hi> of <hi>those</hi> to whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> wrote,<note place="margin">1 Pet. i. 18.</note> was <hi>received by Tradition from their Fathers.</hi> The same was observed long before by the <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> they have walked after the imagination, or as it is in the Margin, after the <hi>stubbornness of their own hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. ix. 14.</note> and after <hi>Baalim</hi> which <hi>their Fathers taught them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And we will burn Incense to the Queen of Heaven:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. xliv. 17.</note> But why so resolute and obstinate in this gross Idolatry? We can expect no good reason for it, <hi>Custom</hi> was their only <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Law. We have done so, and our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before us, our Kings and our Princes in the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>and in the streets of</hi> Jerusalem.</p>
            <p>I know in another place it is made a matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Je. xiv. 3. Deut. xxxii. 17. 2 Kings xv. 3.</note> and an aggravation of their sin, <hi>that they served other Gods whom they knew not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they nor their Fathers: That they served new Gods, newly come up.</hi> And this is noted to the praise of <hi>Aza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> and <hi>Jotham, that they did uprightly in the sight of the Lord, according to all that their Fathers did.</hi> We do also acknowledg that the Religious Customs and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations of the places wherein we live are not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be despised and violated. St. <hi>Paul</hi> alledgeth the <hi>Custom</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> to stop the mouth of contentious <hi>Separatists.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40471:8"/>
            <p> And we have as great a veneration for <hi>Antiquity,</hi> which is truly such, as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to: For it is not the continuance of a thousand years (and few of their Errors are so old) that can make any thing in Religion truly <hi>Ancient,</hi> if it was not so from the beginning. <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>falsehood</hi> will lay claim to all other parts of <hi>Antiquity</hi> as well as <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though we cannot tell of any of our own Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors, beyond the fourth or fifth Generation, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed the same <hi>Religion</hi> in all parts that we do, yet whilst we can make it appear, that the <hi>Religion</hi> which we profess was the <hi>Religion</hi> of our <hi>Lord Christ,</hi> of his <hi>Apostles,</hi> and of the Holy men who lived in the next Ages to them, we cannot justly be taxed with Novelty, or charged with forsaking the God of our Fathers: No <hi>Doctrine</hi> is new which is taught and confirmed by the Authority of <hi>Gods word,</hi> but whatsoever <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Custom</hi> is contrary thereunto, though it hath had a general reception and a long continuance in the Church, yet it hath nothing of true <hi>Antiquity</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it unto us; but I must not pursue this here; having only undertaken to prove that mens immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate zeal for Custom, and the example of their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors, doth oftentimes so blind and bias them that they cannot (or at least will not) discern the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and reason of things, or make an impartial judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Doctrines and Practices in Religion, by which means it comes to pass that they are very obstinate and irreclaimable in their erroneous ways. They will walk every man in the name of his God, in the practice of that <hi>Religion</hi> they have been taught, or bred up in.</p>
            <p>And indeed where <hi>Error</hi> hath but once taken pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, it rules and bears sway, it influences and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the practices of men with the same <hi>absolute</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40471:9"/>
               <hi>unlimited power,</hi> as <hi>Truth</hi> itself doth pretend to: this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Stoicks</hi> call it, this <hi>preoccupation</hi> of <hi>mind,</hi> which is the spring and principle of all the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our life, moves with an equal force when we <hi>mistake,</hi> and when we <hi>think aright;</hi> and a <hi>false persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> will make men as resolute in their Religious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and sufferings as a <hi>true one. Saul</hi> was as zealous for the <hi>Law,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> for the <hi>Gospel:</hi> And while he was under the dominion of a false principle, he was as ready to <hi>persecute</hi> the Disciples of our <hi>Lord,</hi> as he was afterwards to <hi>suffer</hi> for <hi>that name.</hi> And it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servable that nothing could shew him his error but a light from heaven shining round about him. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we hope for the Conversion of any <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Zealot</hi> without many degrees of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> evidence, without an extraordinary, if not a miraculous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</p>
            <p>Indeed the generality of men are in nothing more tenacious than in their Religious persuasions, and there is this rational account to be given why it should be so; because that which is conceived to be their best interest, will justifie their most intent, vigorous and constant prosecution of it: Here tis true, there is the greatest danger of mistaking our methods which should make us examine them well, but when once they are vouched and approved, we are in point of <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Honesty,</hi> as well as in point of <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> bound to proceed in them, which brings me to the third particular, which was this, <hi>viz.</hi> That</p>
            <p n="3">3. We <hi>Christians</hi> are under the strictest obligation of all men <hi>to walk in the name of the Lord our God.</hi> In my insuing Discourse upon this Head, I shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to shew you,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40471:9"/> (1.) What it is to <hi>walk in the name of the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) What our Obligations are to be diligent and constant in so doing, wherein I shall proceed by these degrees; first</p>
            <p n="1">1. To shew how much we <hi>Christians</hi> are obliged thereunto more than any other <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. How much more <hi>we Protestants</hi> than any other <hi>Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. How much more <hi>we</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> in our present Circumstances, than any other <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) I begin with the first, to shew you what it is <hi>to walk in the name of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>name of God</hi> in Scripture frequently signifies that <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> whereby the true <hi>God</hi> is made known, and distinguished from all others, So Psal. xxii. 22. <hi>I will declare thy name unto my Brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John xvii. 6.</note> That of our Saviour can intend nothing else, <hi>I have manifested by name unto the men which thou gavest me out of the world:</hi> That is, I have declared thy <hi>will,</hi> and published thy <hi>Religion</hi> to them. So that in the general, <hi>to walk in the name of the Lord our God,</hi> denotes</p>
            <p n="1">1. An owning and profession of his <hi>Religion,</hi> in opposition to <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A sincere <hi>practice</hi> of what we <hi>profess</hi> in oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and <hi>careless livers.</hi> First, I say,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It denotes an <hi>owning</hi> and <hi>profession</hi> of the true <hi>Religion</hi> in opposition to all <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isaiah xliv. 5.</note> which is well expressed by the <hi>Evangelical Prophet. One shall say, I am the Lords, and another shall call himself by the name of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and another shall sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe with his hand unto the Lord, and Surname him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by the name of</hi> Israel, <hi>that is,</hi> both believing <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40471:10"/>and <hi>Gentiles</hi> shall acknowledg <hi>God</hi> for <hi>their</hi> only <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Master,</hi> and glory in their Relation to him.</p>
            <p>It consists in an owning of our <hi>Religion</hi> when it is most <hi>maligned</hi> and <hi>persecuted,</hi> professing <hi>Christs name</hi> when it is <hi>every where spoken against,</hi> not <hi>falling away in a time of temptation.</hi> But then especially <hi>confessing our Saviour before men,</hi> when by so doing we bring our selves into disgrace and danger. For which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian courage of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> stands upon honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Record. When they were commanded <hi>not to speak at all,</hi> nor to teach <hi>in the name of Jesus,</hi> no threatnings could silence them,<note place="margin">Acts iv. 18, 19.</note>
               <hi>we cannot but speak the things which we have seen and heard.</hi> And we also may properly be said <hi>to walk in Gods name,</hi> if in these diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and perillous times we do not only with <hi>the heart believe unto righteousness, but with the mouth make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession unto salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But seeing our actions profess better for us than our words, and our light shines most brightly before men when they see our good works: therefore though we may be said to have entered upon this walk, to have begun well our Christian course by the profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the true Religion, and a subscription to the Articles of the Church in opposition to Infidels and Heretical dissenters, yet then only in a</p>
            <p n="2">2. Place are we said to proceed and walk on in this name when we add <hi>sincerity</hi> and <hi>perseverance</hi> of <hi>Practice</hi> to this <hi>Profession,</hi> in opposition to <hi>Hypocrites</hi> or <hi>loose livers.</hi> Many that did not only <hi>profess Christs name,</hi> but <hi>also Prophesied in it,</hi> and in <hi>that name did many wonderful works</hi> (as wonderful perhaps as any of those the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> boasts of) Yet our <hi>blessed Saviour</hi> disowns them, and casts them off for their <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John vii. 23.</note>
               <hi>I never knew you, depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40471:10"/>
            <p> We cannot in the sense of my <hi>Text</hi> be said <hi>to walk in the name of God,</hi> or of <hi>Christ,</hi> meerly because we call him <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> or have his <hi>name named upon us,</hi> and are called <hi>Christians;</hi> unless we <hi>depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> unless we do <hi>the will of our Father,</hi> unless we tread in our <hi>Saviours</hi> steps, <hi>do the things which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us,</hi> and <hi>walk as we have had him for an example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know none more faulty and defective herein than those men who pretend most to perfection, I mean our <hi>modern Romans</hi> who affect not only their <hi>Praenomina</hi> but <hi>Cognomina</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> who, as if it were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be called <hi>Christians,</hi> will lay claim to the other name of our Lord, and be <hi>Jesuites</hi> too; how well they <hi>walk in this name</hi> let their <hi>mercy,</hi> their <hi>meekness,</hi> their <hi>gentleness towards all men, their subjection to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and <hi>those that are in Authority,</hi> their <hi>quiet and peaceable behaviour testifie.</hi> Or rather let their <hi>hellish Conspiracies,</hi> their <hi>turbulent disordering of all Christian Kingdoms,</hi> their cruel and barbarous <hi>Massacres</hi> and <hi>Assassinations,</hi> their dissembled <hi>Friendships</hi> and real <hi>Perfidiousness,</hi> shame their <hi>Hypocrisie.</hi> For how <hi>grosly</hi> have these <hi>bloody</hi> and <hi>deceitful men</hi> belied their Masters best name, and by their Practices told the <hi>world</hi> that he <hi>was</hi> therefore <hi>called Jesus,</hi> not because he came <hi>to save mens lives,</hi> but <hi>to destroy them.</hi> And if I had time, I might justly reflect upon some <hi>Hypocrites</hi> of another <hi>Denomination</hi> (though acted, I doubt not, by <hi>these mens</hi> influence and instigation) who have <hi>boasted</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves as much <hi>in the name</hi> of the Lord, and as much <hi>dishonoured it,</hi> who have first <hi>lifted up their hands to God in prayer,</hi> and <hi>Covenanting,</hi> and then <hi>lifted them up against his Servants,</hi> against <hi>his Anointed,</hi> against <hi>his King</hi> and <hi>his Priests,</hi> in acts of the most unnatural Rebellion and inhuman Cruelty, but I shall conclude
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40471:11"/>this Head in a more general reflection, relating in some degree to us all: We all go thus far in the way of the Lord, we all profess the <hi>Christian Faith</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition to <hi>Jews, Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> and the <hi>Christian Protestant Faith</hi> in distinction from <hi>Papists,</hi> and the <hi>Christian Protestant Holy Faith,</hi> in distinction from <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Protestants</hi> at <hi>large:</hi> but this will not denominate us upright <hi>walkers in Gods name,</hi> unless we shew forth out of a good Conversation our works with meekness of wisdom. Our <hi>Profession,</hi> nay our <hi>Faith,</hi> will do us no good unless it make us good, good <hi>Magistrates,</hi> good <hi>Subjects,</hi> good <hi>men,</hi> unless it work upon the heart and make that sound and good, unless it work upon the life and make that regular and good, unless it be the soul of obedience; the reason or internal Law of the mind, which sets all our facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and members on work, and presents unto us the whole Royalty of the Law, breaks the sway of inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections, rebates and turns the violence of corrupt inclinations, and persuades us above all Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to take up the <hi>Yoke</hi> and the <hi>Cross</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi> But to be a little more particular,</p>
            <p>Our <hi>walking in the name of the Lord our God,</hi> may be reduced to these three Instances,
<list>
                  <item>1. Our affiance in his Power and Goodness.</item>
                  <item>2. Our submission to his Authority.</item>
                  <item>3. Our zeal for his Glory.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Isaiah l. 10. Psal. xx. 5.</note> Our affiance in his power and goodness: When in our greatest distresses <hi>we can trust in the name of the Lord, and stay our selves upon our God,</hi> when after our deliverances, we <hi>can rejoyce in his salvation, and in the name of our God set up our banners:</hi> When under the most unjust oppressions we can <hi>commit our cause to God who judgeth righteously,</hi> and in the prosperity of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40471:11"/>our affairs, <hi>boast in God all the day long,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. xliv. 8.</note>
               <hi>and praise his name for ever:</hi> When neither the <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>honour</hi> nor <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>disgrace,</hi> when neither threatnings nor so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations can move us from our stedfastness in <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or tempt us to faulter in our <hi>Christian Conformity:</hi> we hereby make it appear that we do indeed believe an over-ruling Providence, and confide in Almighty goodness, which is <hi>one way of walking in the name of the Lord.</hi> We may be said to do so in a second place:</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we submit to his Authority, not going <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the word of the Lord our God to do less or more, not daring to reject any of his Commands,</hi> nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any other in opposition to them. To break <hi>Gods Laws</hi> in the <hi>Popes name,</hi> relying either upon his <hi>Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation</hi> in <hi>hand,</hi> or his <hi>Pardon</hi> in <hi>Reversion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When we so own <hi>Gods Sovereignty</hi> as to shake off the <hi>Dominion</hi> of all <hi>Ʋsurpers,</hi> not suffering sin to <hi>reign</hi> in our <hi>mortal bodies</hi> or the <hi>Man of sin</hi> to give law to our <hi>Consciences,</hi> and Captivate us in a blind obedience to all the <hi>Dictates</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi> of his <hi>Chair;</hi> in a word when we call no <hi>Man Master upon earth,</hi> nor do the <hi>will of the flesh,</hi> but in all things shew a ready, constant and uniform compliance with the Divine Will, then do we take the <hi>Lord</hi> for our <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>walk in his name by owning his Supremacy,</hi> and submitting to his <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> But there is somthing more meant by walking in Gods name; not the exercise of a distinct vertue, but the improvement of those we have named already. The Heroical degree or perfection of them which in a third.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Place we called <hi>Zeal</hi> for <hi>Gods glory,</hi> the honor of his Religion, the interest of his Church; and the necessity of this <hi>Zeal,</hi> to our good proceeding and perseverance in our Christian course, is implied in these
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40471:12"/>words of <hi>Resolution, We will walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever and ever.</hi> They found it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to warm and inflame their affections, to excite and carry on their endeavours in Gods service by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the most proper motives, that they might raise in themselves an holy emulation by observing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens practices, and attain a <hi>real excellency</hi> by stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to out do those who most eagerly pursued an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior,</hi> if not an <hi>imaginary good, Every man will walk in the name of his God,</hi> and we will not for shame come short of Idolaters, but if possible exceed and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strip them in the most fervent Acts of their Devotion. We serve the true God who deserves, and can requite our most exact, our most painful and costly obedience. By such Arguments as these, we may suppose they thought it necessary to kindle such a Holy Zeal in their hearts as might confirm and keep up their Pious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions, and enable them to <hi>walk in the name of the Lord for ever:</hi> And without some good degrees of this Zeal we shall make but a very heavy and flow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress in Religion, we shall do no great things for God, for his name, his house, his servants, nor for our own fouls, and therefore the <hi>Apostle</hi> observes, <hi>that it is good to be zealously affected always in a good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Zeal in itself is one of those things which the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of a middle nature,<note place="margin">Gal. iv. 18.</note> neither good nor evil, but may become either as it is differently cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstantiated, by the Heathen Writers it is usually taken in a bad sense, and fignifies <hi>Emulation,</hi> and that sort of it which proceeds from <hi>Envy,</hi> and breaks out in too eager contention: But when we take it in a good sense, as it is often taken in Scripture, it signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies an intention of Holy affections, a strong bent of the mind, a restless motion of soul, after Heaven
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40471:12"/>and Heavenly things: More particularly it denotes three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A vehement love and affection to the things of God: such as <hi>David</hi> expressed upon all occasions,<note place="margin">Psal. cxix. 167. Psal. xvi. 2. Psal. lxxxiv, 10.</note>
               <hi>I have kept thy Commandments, and I love them exceedingly. All my delight is in thy Saints which excel in vertue. I had rather be a door-keeper in the house of the Lord, than to dwell in the tents of wickedness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It imports extream grief and indignation to see that which we love despised, and injured, this we see also exemplified in the forementioned <hi>Holy man, Rivers of tears,</hi> saith he, <hi>run down mine eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. cxix. 136.</note>
               <hi>because the wicked forsake thy Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It imports earnestness and forwardness in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and vindicating the <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>Worship,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> when they are reproached, corrupted, or any ways endangered; this Zeal was remarkable in <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Josiah,</hi> those <hi>truly good and sincere refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers:</hi> And in <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> when he purged the Temple. The Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it,<note place="margin">Phil. i. 27.</note> a <hi>striving for the Faith of the Gospel. Stand fast in one spirit, in one mind, striving together for the Faith of the Gospel, and in nothing terrified by your adversaries, which is to them an evident token of Perdition, but to you of salvation and that from God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 4.</note> The Apostle <hi>Jude</hi> calls it <hi>a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for the faith that was once delivered to the Saints.</hi> So that you see a <hi>zeal</hi> for Gods Glory im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies a vehement affection to the <hi>Ways,</hi> the <hi>Worship,</hi> the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> the <hi>Servants</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> a Holy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation at any contempt or abuse of them, an earnest contention in our proper places to maintain and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate them.</p>
            <p>We must confess <hi>Gods name</hi> hath by no one thing been more <hi>dishonoured,</hi> the <hi>beauty</hi> of <hi>Religion defaced,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40471:13"/>the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church disturbed,</hi> than by the heats, the hurries, and violences of some mens spirits, who would pass for <hi>holy zealots,</hi> stout promoters and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of <hi>Gods Cause;</hi> we have known too well the ill effects of a turbulent and inordinate Zeal, when too many under a pretence of acting for the <hi>Glory</hi> of God have despised and vilified the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of God, <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Ecclesiastical,</hi> diminished the reputation of their Governours both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> advancing their slanders and calumnies, which is worst of all from their <hi>Persons</hi> to their <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay it would be well in comparison if they went no farther than <hi>diminution</hi> and <hi>calumnies.</hi> But, alas, the dint of their Religious fury hath gone much deeper in many <hi>direful attempts</hi> heretofore, and in the late most <hi>barbarous</hi> and <hi>horrid murder</hi> of the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> the story is so fresh that I need not mention here the aggravating circumstances of it. I confess the excursions and outrages of this wild Zeal, in many persons and in some societies, is a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that we can hardly speak of with that temper and sobriety of mind we ought to preserve; whilst we condemn their excesses, it will be hard to avoid all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of transport in our selves: Therefore I leave the Argument; I have no time to shew to you at large how our Zeal must be bounded and regulated, that it may become truly pious.</p>
            <p>I can only observe to you very briefly, that our Zeal must
<list>
                  <item>1. Be grounded in Knowledg.</item>
                  <item>2. It must be managed with Prudence.</item>
                  <item>3. It must be attended with Charity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It must be a <hi>Zeal according to knowledg,</hi> we must be sure that it be always imployed in a <hi>good thing,</hi> not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40471:13"/>only that the end we aim at be good, but that the means we use for the obtaining of that end be so too. We must <hi>not speak, much less act, wickedly for God,</hi> or <hi>talk deceitfully for him:</hi> our Zeal must take light from the Word, fire from the Sanctuary, we must be sure that we have a calling, a warrant, and a good ground to go upon, and whatever the <hi>Jus zelotarum</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews, it will concern us to know this espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that neither the <hi>Laws</hi> of our <hi>Land,</hi> nor the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> doth allow any private person out of any pretended zeal for God, to do execution imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon a Malefactor, without expecting the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Court of Judicature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our zeal must be guided by prudence and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, it must be wise, as well as warm, we must <hi>observe time and judgment as</hi> Solomon <hi>speaks,</hi> mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating our selves according to the occasion, raising the degrees of our zeal proportionably to the value of the things it is exercised about, not spending all our indignation about a trifle, nor putting forth our whole strength to that which we may remove with a little finger: Zeal must be like the fire which we keep up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Hearths, but inlarge or lessen it according to the occasions of the house, we must be always <hi>zealously</hi> affected, always have that holy fire alive in our hearts, but blow it up, or abate it, according as the Cause, wherein we have to deal, doth require.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our Zeal must be attended with Charity, our hatred of sin must not proceed to malice against the sinner, neither must our <hi>zeal,</hi> for truth, destroy our <hi>good will</hi> and <hi>love</hi> to our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> no not to our very <hi>Enemies,</hi> not to the Enemies of our Religion. There is nothing of Bitterness, Cruelty, or Revenge in the true <hi>Christian</hi> temper, as appears by that notable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40471:14"/>rebuke which our <hi>Saviour</hi> gave to his <hi>Disciples,</hi> when they desired him to command <hi>fire</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> to <hi>consume</hi> the <hi>Samaritans;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke ix. 55.</note>
               <hi>Ye know not what manner of spirit ye are of.</hi> Those <hi>Samaritans</hi> were persons as obnoxious and ill-deserving, as great <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schismaticks</hi> in Religion as any again; their behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our towards our <hi>Saviours person</hi> very unworthy and affronting, and their disrespect to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> the place of his worship, no less remarkable; yet our <hi>Saviour</hi> disallows of cruelty even towards them, because that in any case is inconsistent with the <hi>design</hi> of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the great end of his coming into the world. <hi>The son of man is not come to destroy mens lives, but to save them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Sprat.</note> Too many indeed, <hi>as an excellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son expresses it,</hi> believe no Religion to be pure but what is intemperately rigid, no Zeal to be spiritual but what is censorious or vindicative, whereas no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is true that is not peaceable, as well as pure. No Zeal is Spiritual that is not also Charitable, nay chiefly so.</p>
            <p>I have shewed you now what it is to <hi>walk in the name of the Lord our God,</hi> viz. to trust in his Power and Goodness, to submit to his Authority, and to be <hi>zealously affected always in a good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed to shew that we Christians are more obliged to Diligence, Zeal, Constancy in the practice of our Religion than any other. Here I proposed to proceed by these degrees, <hi>viz.</hi> to shew
<list>
                  <item>1. How much more <hi>Christians,</hi> as such, are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged than any other <hi>sort</hi> or <hi>sect</hi> of men.</item>
                  <item>2. How much more we <hi>Protestants,</hi> than any other <hi>Christians.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. How much more we of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in our present circumstances, than any other <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40471:14"/> 1. I say we <hi>Christians</hi> are under more powerful obligations to Diligence, Seriousness, and stedfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in <hi>our</hi> Religion, than any other men in <hi>theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never any <hi>Religion</hi> or Institution in the world, made such clear and full discoveries of mens Duties, or afforded more considerable helps to practice than the <hi>Christian</hi> doth. The <hi>Apostles</hi> thought it the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est contradiction to their Profession, for any men to be called <hi>Christians</hi> and yet to live in the practice of their former sins.<note place="margin">1 Pet. iv. 3.</note>
               <hi>Let the time past of your life suffice you,</hi> saith <hi>St.</hi> Peter, <hi>to have wrought the will of the Gentiles,</hi> that is, that <hi>time past</hi> when you were no <hi>Christians. Let us who are of the day be sober,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Thes. v. 8.</note> saith St. <hi>Paul:</hi> intimating to them the powerful influence that the <hi>Gospel</hi> hath upon a Pious, Vertuous, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Conversation, in regard of the clearness of the Revelations therein contained, which may more fully appear to us, if we compare <hi>this day,</hi> either to the glimmering <hi>light of nature,</hi> or that which God was pleased to vouchsafe to his <hi>own People, the Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our understanding, <hi>saith Solomon,</hi> is the <hi>Candle of the Lord,</hi> but as the light of the Sun will put out a Candle, so that faint and weak light of Nature, by which the <hi>Heathens groped</hi> after God in the <hi>night of Ignorance,</hi> must disappear when compared to the brightness <hi>of the Sun of Righteousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thus the <hi>Prophet</hi> describes our Condition,<note place="margin">Isai. viii. 27.</note> when <hi>Christ</hi> came among us. <hi>He shall look upon the Earth, and behold darkness and dimness, and the shadow of death,</hi> and</p>
            <p n="2">2. The light of the <hi>Mosaical dispensation</hi> was not without a great Alloy, or mixture of <hi>darkness,</hi> the Points of our Salvation were but obscurely sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed in the <hi>Typical</hi> or <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> but are now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40471:15"/>made manifest, fully revealed by him <hi>who brought life and immortality to light in the Gospel.</hi> It would be easie and pertinent to enlarge upon these Heads, if I had time, as also to shew you that the <hi>Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> doth furnish us with the most prevalent motives and inducements to Piety and Vertue, as giving us the knowledg of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> his Providence and Goodness, the knowledg of the beauty, and of the rewards of Vertue, and also of the Doctrine of Remission of sins, which things were never so fully and fairly represented by any as by our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apostles.</hi> But I cannot stay to consider them. I would only observe in the general, that the service re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of <hi>us,</hi> is much more easie, and reasonable, than what was expected under the <hi>legal dispensation.</hi> Under the Gospel we have no costly <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> no bloody <hi>Sacraments,</hi> no burdensom <hi>Ceremonies:</hi> all the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Institutions</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> are in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree reasonable and useful, there is nothing comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him which is not really good, becoming the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of God, and agreeable to the <hi>Reason</hi> of man: nothing forbidden by him but what debaucheth our understanding, pollutes our minds, disturbs our quiet, impairs our bodily strength and vigour, and some way or other impedes the Welfare, the Peace, the Health, and Comfort of mankind. For what is that he would have us <hi>learn</hi> of him? Or what did <hi>He</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> Preach and Press upon his followers, but the exercise of those vertues that do perfect and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble our natures, make us like unto God, happy in our selves, and publick blessings to others? What an aggravation then of folly and wickedness, is it in Christians to be disobedient to so good a Master? To refuse so profitable and pleasant a service, wherein <hi>duty</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40471:15"/>and <hi>interest, work</hi> and <hi>wages</hi> meet together: <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>honour, righteousness</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> sweetly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine and kiss each other. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the advantages <hi>of Protestants,</hi> so their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are greater than any other <hi>Christians,</hi> than any of the <hi>Romish Communion,</hi> those <hi>whose eyes,</hi> he who rivals that title of the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>God of this world, hath blinded,</hi> locking up the Scriptures from them in an unknown tongue, not instructing them in any other Doctrines, so much as those of <hi>Implicite Faith</hi> and <hi>blind Obedience:</hi> Many errors and imperfections may easily be excused in that Devotion, which is the <hi>Child</hi> of <hi>Ignorance:</hi> Any sin will be adventured on, where men are taught the pardon will be as easie, and we know those that are committed in the <hi>Cause</hi> and for the <hi>Interest</hi> of holy <hi>Church,</hi> how great soever, are wiped off with a gentle <hi>Pennance,</hi> if not with a free and absolute <hi>forgiveness,</hi> yea if it be a bold and daring Crime, such as <hi>Treason</hi> or <hi>Murder,</hi> tis by one of <hi>Romes</hi> miraculous <hi>transmutations,</hi> not only made a Vertue, but a meritorious one too.</p>
            <p>No wonder if they Pray short and seldom to <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> in the name of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> when the <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Invocation</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the <hi>Virgin Mother</hi> (though without any reason, or the least shew of Authority from Scripture) is made the principal part of their Religion: no wonder that the common people do not scruple the worshipping of <hi>Images,</hi> seeing their <hi>Teachers</hi> have made them <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> without the <hi>Second,</hi> by dividing the <hi>Tenth</hi> into <hi>Two.</hi> No wonder that so many forswear themselves against the <hi>Third Commandment,</hi> whilst they believe the <hi>Popes</hi> power of relaxing <hi>Oaths.</hi> The <hi>Lords-day</hi> must needs lose much of its regard and due observation in such a number of other <hi>Festivals;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40471:16"/>nor can the <hi>Fifth Commandment</hi> keep any good order in Families or Kingdoms, whilst the <hi>Pope</hi> takes upon him to <hi>depose Princes,</hi> and absolve <hi>Subjects</hi> from their <hi>Allegiance:</hi> And since the Doctrine of putting <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> to death, the <hi>Sixth Commandment</hi> hath been but a weak <hi>Life-Guard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can the <hi>Seventh</hi> hinder <hi>incestuous</hi> marriages, or continue <hi>lawful</hi> ones, if <hi>Rome</hi> think fit to <hi>dispense</hi> or to <hi>divorce:</hi> And we know <hi>Princes</hi> under the same Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority have leaped over the <hi>Eighth</hi> to invade the just rights of their Neighbours, and the <hi>Ninth</hi> must signifie as little, since <hi>Equivocation</hi> was tolerated, and <hi>some</hi> think they have quite disanulled the <hi>Tenth,</hi> by teaching that Concupiscence is no sin.</p>
            <p>No wonder if a <hi>Religion</hi> thus <hi>corrupted, Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> thus <hi>weakned</hi> and <hi>perverted,</hi> have little force and efficacy in the government of mens lives, nay I must declare to you thatsome of their principles have such a direct tendency to deprave mens manners, that if they can be so unreasonable as to believe them, it is next to impossible they should hold honest and good in their practices.</p>
            <p>It is the great <hi>mercy of God</hi> that hath <hi>disintangled</hi> us from such a <hi>Yoke,</hi> that hath <hi>brought</hi> us out of their <hi>darkness</hi> into a <hi>marvelous light,</hi> that we are allowed to read and hear Gods word in a language we all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand: that we are permitted to <hi>try the spirits,</hi> and to examine the <hi>Doctrins</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> which are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to us. That we are required to believe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without <hi>Scripture</hi> Authority: nothing against the evidence of <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Sense,</hi> that we have a <hi>reasonable service</hi> without bodily and unprositable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, without a multitude of fond and <hi>Superstitious Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40471:16"/>
            <p> By these and many other blessed advantages of the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> are our obligations strengthned to <hi>abound</hi> in Gods service, to be <hi>fruitful in every good word and work,</hi> to do <hi>the will of God from the heart,</hi> and to <hi>walk in his name for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We especially of the <hi>Church of England</hi> ought to be very <hi>exact</hi> and <hi>exemplary</hi> in our obedience, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our Church hath some advantages above any other: if not in her <hi>Doctrines,</hi> yet in her <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> forasmuch as in it that <hi>order</hi> and <hi>discipline</hi> is upheld, which is best fitted to preserve an even and sober temper in <hi>Religion,</hi> between the extravaganties of <hi>Enthusiasm</hi> and the follies of <hi>Superstition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrins contained in our Articles of Religion are so warily expressed, and in such a latitude, that differing parties will subscribe to them.</p>
            <p>There is no <hi>Protestant</hi> Church in the world but will say <hi>Amen</hi> to all our Prayers.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are but few and those very <hi>decent,</hi> and we use them not as necessary in themselves, but in obedience to that Authority which every Church hath over its own Members.</p>
            <p>Our Ministers of Holy things are Consecrated and Ordained according to the <hi>Scripture</hi> and the <hi>Canons</hi> of the Universal Church. In a word, so excellent is the temper of our present Settlement, that there is no such Church in the world, with which men of differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing persuasions may more safely Communicate, under which Dissenters, if they be peaceable, may live more happily: much more might be said of the good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of this Church, and if I had time I might recount many singular blessings and deliverances, which do oblige and ought to encourage us above others to an extraordinary diligence in Gods service.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40471:17"/>Our <hi>Luke-warmness</hi> and indifferency in Religion will be more intolerable than other mens <hi>Profaness</hi> and total neglect of it. And great mercies, if abused, will end in as signal judgments. <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos ii. 2.</note> says God, by his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> to that people, as he might say unto us, and we should be apt to think he had a great blessing for those he takes such notice of, but it seems they had slighted his goodness: whereupon it follows, <hi>therefore will I visit upon you all your iniquities.</hi> Let us not boast of our priviledges, The <hi>Temple of the Lord are these.</hi> Let us not think over-well of our selves, because we are members of the best Church in the world, and because God hath owned us by as gracious and wonderful preservations and deliverances, as perhaps he ever did any people. But let us endeavour to improve these priviledges, and walk worthy of so great benefits, and to secure them to our selves by our Diligence, our Zeal, our Constancy in Gods service, not <hi>glorying,</hi> but <hi>walking in the name of the Lord our God for ever and ever,</hi> that we may make it appear that we who are of the true Church, are true Christians, <hi>a peculiar people zealous of good works.</hi> The Policy and Power of our <hi>Enemies</hi> we know at this time is very active and menacing, yet nothing bodes greater evil to us than our own <hi>Ʋnchristian,</hi> our own <hi>Ʋnprotestant</hi> lives, the general declension of Holy <hi>Zeal</hi> in all sorts and degrees of men. Wherefore that we may be <hi>Friends</hi> to our selves in the midst of so many <hi>Enemies,</hi> true to our own interest, when so many have combined against it, that we may keep <hi>God</hi> our friend when men rise up against us:</p>
            <p>Let me in the close of all humbly entreat and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you, both Magistrates and others, in your several
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40471:17"/>places to do the work of God, and of Religion, with all <hi>your might,</hi> with the greatest intension and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency of spirit, to imitate the Zeal of Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, and to retrieve that <hi>seriousness</hi> in Religion, which hath been observed to be the particular <hi>Genius</hi> of this Nation, even at such times when it fell infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely short of those great advantages which it now enjoys.</p>
            <p>I would exhort you to be <hi>Zealous</hi> for, 1. the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished Protestant Religion of our Country,</hi> against all <hi>Heretical</hi> and <hi>Schismatical</hi> opposers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That you would express that <hi>Zeal</hi> especially in the practice and promotion of the plain and indisputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble duties in our <hi>Common Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I say it concerns us very much at this time to be <hi>zealous</hi> for the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> not only in regard of its <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>excellency,</hi> but also in regard of the <hi>manifold oppositions</hi> that are made against it, insomuch that we are in great danger of <hi>losing</hi> it, unless every man in his place appear with <hi>Christian</hi> Courage and Zeal for its <hi>preservation,</hi> and we betray the best Cause in the world, if we do not act in it with a heat and resolution proportionable to theirs that seek to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it; <hi>shall every man walk in the name of his God, and sacrifice his</hi> All <hi>to a fond opinion?</hi> Shall <hi>Papists</hi> be <hi>Zealous</hi> for their <hi>Images, Phanaticks</hi> for their <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations,</hi> and shall we only esteem it the goodness and wisdom of our <hi>moderation,</hi> not to concern our selves too far for the <hi>honor</hi> of the true <hi>God,</hi> and for the <hi>defence</hi> of that Religion whose worth we have proved and known so well? Or do we think to secure our selves by a <hi>faint resistance</hi> when our Enemies bear up so <hi>powerfully</hi> against us? No, <hi>Magistrates</hi> must im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all the strength of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Justice, Ministers</hi> must <hi>reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long-suffering</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40471:18"/>and every man must do all that he lawfully can for the <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>safety</hi> of his Religion; and consider I beseech you, that if we will <hi>contend</hi> for the truth as we ought, whilst the brunt is not so sharp, whilst the duty of <hi>contending</hi> is upon easier terms than blood, we may be excused from the necessity of a more fiery <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> our devout Prayers, our exemplary Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations, our Godly Sorrow for sin past, and our dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent care to avoid it for the future, may possibly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse our <hi>Lives</hi> and save our <hi>Estates:</hi> Which minds me to Exhort you in a second place, though but in a word, to express your <hi>Zeal</hi> for Religion especially in the practice and promotion of the plain and indisputable duties of our <hi>Common Christianity,</hi> we are all agreed that <hi>Righteousness, Sobriety, Mercy, Meekness, Humility, Purity,</hi> &amp;c. are vertues recommended to us by the common dictates of natural light, and powerfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our great <hi>Master</hi> and his <hi>Apostles.</hi> Let us then, I beseech you, in the fear of God apply our selves to the serious and affectionate practice of these vertues and graces. I have not time to propound the motives that offer themselves to quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and raise our sluggish spirits. It is enough that we cherish hopes of <hi>everlasting happiness,</hi> that we look for a reward from our <hi>Heavenly Master,</hi> for if so, why are we not about his <hi>Work?</hi> why do we not endeavor to live up to the <hi>Rules</hi> of his <hi>Religion? To purifie our selves as he is pure, to be merciful as he is merciful, to be filled with all the fruits of Righteousness which are by Christ Jesus, unto the glory and praise of God.</hi> Would to God I could speak to you with the spirit and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, as well as the words of that great <hi>Apostle: My dearly beloved brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. xv. 58.</note>
               <hi>be stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as you know that your labor shall not be in vain in the Lord:</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40471:18"/>and again, <hi>Let us not be weary of well doing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. vi. 9.</note>
               <hi>for in due season we shall reap, if we faint not.</hi> How can an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation <hi>commenced</hi> with so much love, pursued with so much <hi>earnestness,</hi> sweetned with such <hi>gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises</hi> possibly miscarry? In the same breath that we hear of our <hi>Work</hi> we hear of our <hi>Reward</hi> too, a little short <hi>Work,</hi> a great and eternal <hi>Reward.</hi> What a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful invitation is this to all that believe, to <hi>turn from every evil way,</hi> and to be <hi>Holy as he that hath called us is holy in all manner of conversation?</hi> If any temptation assault us, and begin to shake the constancy of our Christian Resolution, what considerations more likely to settle us? to make us stedfast and unmoveable in the work of the Lord? As we know that the temptations which flatter us are very moving, as we feel the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the pleasures and advantages of this world, so we are assured that if we persevere in holiness, <hi>and walk in the name of the Lord for ever and ever,</hi> there are infinitely better things to counterbalance and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie the fairest of all the temptations that solicite us. <hi>Wherefore the rather, brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. i. 10.</note>
               <hi>give all diligence to make your calling and election sure, for if ye do these things ye shall never fall, for so an</hi> entrance shall be <hi>administred to you abundantly into the everlasting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</hi> To whom <hi>with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Father and ever blessed Spirit of Grace, be ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of us, and all his servants all honor, glory, power, and praise henceforth and for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord of all power and might, who art the Author and giver of all good things: graft in our hearts the Love of thy name, increase in us true Religion, nourish us with all goodness, and of thy great mercy keep us in the same, through Jesus Christ our Lord,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>